Contact

Email:

sthan18@terpmail.umd.edu

Phone:

(410)-419-2169

Address:

2617 Luiss Deane Drive, Parkville, Maryland, USA

Online Portfolio

Personal Website:

http://nikeshshrestha2000.github.io/

LinkedIn:

https://www.linkedin.com/in/nikesh-shrestha-3518ba11b/

Education

Bachelor of Science Mechanical Engineering University of Maryland College Park, MD, USA GPA: 3.6/4.0

Calvert Hall College High School Towson, MD, USA

GPA: 4.0/4.0

Skills

Technical Skills

3D Design (SolidWorks, Inventor, AutoCAD)

Microsoft Office

Simulation (ANSYS Fluent, COMSOL Multiphysics)

Programming Skills

MATLAB & Simulink

Python

C++

HTML

Machines

MakerBot 3D Printer Bandsaw, Lathe, Belt Sander Soldering Iron

Languages

Fluent in English Fluent in Nepali Conversant in French

Nikesh Shrestha

Bachelor of Science in Mechanical Engineering

Summary

Mechanical Engineering graduate from the University of Maryland – College Park (Aug. 2018 – Dec. 2021) with experience in research and engineering projects. Awarded multiple awards for excellence in education. Experienced various technical and soft skills through courses, projects, self-education, and involvement in multiple organizations.

Work Experience

Nano Biochip for Disease Detection, Diagnosis and Monitoring (New Jersey Institute of Technology) (NSF REU)

[Jun. 2020 – Aug. 2020]

- Research Assistant in NJIT Advanced Energy Systems and Microdevices Laboratory.
- Developed a MATLAB algorithm for autonomous measurement of wetting angles from images.
- Investigated the visualization and characterization of fluid drop on a surface treated PDMS, and flow dynamics in PDMS microchannel for implementation in a passive plasma separation.

Undergraduate Teaching Assistant (University of Maryland) [Aug. 2020 – Dec. 2021]

- Undergraduate Teaching Assistant for Electronics and Instrumentation II; Vibrations, Controls and Optimization I; Introductory C++ & MATLAB Programming Course.
- Led lab and studio sessions with 20 to 30 students.
- Guided students with understanding course concepts and applying them to assignments.

Technical Experience

Project: Redesigning Braking System for Triathlon Bikes

- Team Leader and Team Scribe.
- Designed and built a hydraulic braking system integrated inside aerobars for Triathlon bikes.
- Implemented the Product Development Process.
- Used MATLAB, SolidWorks for design, analysis, and simulation.
- Used additive and subtractive manufacturing machines for construction.
- Presented the working prototype at the University of Maryland Design Day.

Project: Time Series Analysis: Location Prediction of Dynamical System

- Applied Machine Learning Algorithm to forecast the location and orientation of a Navy Battleship.
- Implemented Supervised Probabilistic Model: Variational Sparse Gaussian Processes.
- Utilized Probabilistic Programming language in Python: PyMC3.

Project: Designed and built an Autonomous Robot

- Designed and built a sensor car that autonomously follows the operator.
- Utilized Arduino Uno microcontroller, sensors, and actuators to autonomously detect and follow the operator at various speeds.
- Programmed using Arduino IDE and Processing 3 for operation and demonstration.

Project: Disassembly and Mechanical Analysis of HP Vista Personal Computer

- Design, Reliability and Cost analysis of Graphics and Memory Controller chip, and RAM.
- Visualized the manufacturing considerations for thermo-mechanical and vibrational effects.
- Disassembled individual components on a computer motherboard for analysis.
- Used subtractive manufacturing machines for breakdown and polishing of components.

Awards & Honors

- National Science Foundation REU Fellowship
- Dean's List for Outstanding Students
- Office of Multi-ethnic Student Education Academic Excellence Award
- G. Lee and Lou Ann Lushbaugh, Jr. Endowed Scholarship
- Sean and Sarah Durbin Scholarship
- Bechtel Corporate Partner Scholarship